Finding Aid for the Tennessee Williams Papers LSC.0492
UCLA Library Special Collections
Tennessee Williams papers
1930-1970
UCLA Library Special Collections
Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983
LSC.0492
0.8 linear feet (2 boxes)
Thomas Lanier Williams (1911-1983) was born in Columbus, Missouri. He won a Pulitzer Prize in 1948 for A Streetcar Named Desire, and another in 1955 for Cat on a Hot Tin Roof. Many of his plays were adapted for the screen. His works include 24 major plays, 2 novels, several screenplays, and a volume of memoirs. The collection contains manuscripts of several of Williams' published and unpublished plays, play fragments, short stories, screen scenarios, and poems.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Online Items Available note for the link to the digitized materials.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Tennessee Williams, 1970.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9936492433606533
Biography
Thomas Lanier Williams was born on March 26, 1911 in Columbus, Mississippi. His first major success came with the 1945 Broadway premiere of The Glass Menagerie. He won a Pulitzer Prize in 1948 for A Streetcar Named Desire and another in 1955 for Cat on a Hot Tin Roof. Williams adapted a number of his plays for the screen, and his works include 24 major plays, 2 novels, several screenplays, and a volume of memoirs. Williams died on February 25, 1983 in New York City.
Scope and Content
Collection contains manuscripts of several of Williams' published and unpublished plays, play fragments, short stories, screen scenarios, and poems. Includes transcripts of early versions of Sweet Bird of Youth and The Night of the Iguana. Also includes uncorrected proofs and galleys of Gilbert Maxwell's book, Tennessee Williams and Friends (1965).
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Tennessee Williams Papers (1 item).
Dramatists, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Maxwell, Gilbert -- Tennessee Williams and Friends.; Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983--Archives.
- The Day on Which a Man Dies (an occidental Noh Play). Miami, 1960; 40 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- And Tell Sad Stories of the Deaths of Queens... Havana, Cuba, circa 1958; 33 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Now and at the Hour of Our Death. n.p., undated; 39 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The Demolition Downtown. n.p., undated; 31 leaves. Mimeograph and a few hand-typed pages with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- No Sight Would Be Worth Seeing. n.p., undated; 20 leaves. Mimeograph and a few hand-typed pages with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Drunken Fiddler. v.p., circa 1930-1940; 72 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Happy August the Tenth. n.p., unpublished short story, 1957; 21 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Stairs to the Roof. New Orleans, unpublished play, 1941; 105 leaves. Professionally typed. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Scope and Contents note
  Produced at the Pasadena Playhouse, circa 1943.
- Sweet Bird of Youth. n.p., circa 1955; 80 leaves. Mimeograph and a few hand-typed pages, with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Original version, produced at Studio M in Coral Gables, Florida, circa 1956.
- The Milk Train Doesn't Stop Here Anymore. n.p., undated; 65 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Fragments.
- Do it Yourself Interview. n.p., undated; 15 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Candles to the Sun. n.p., unpublished play, 1936; 53 leaves. Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- The Night of the Iguana. n.p., undated; 50 leaves. Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Early version, produced 1960.
- The Twister. n.p., unpublished and unproduced, undated; 12 leaves. Typescript, carbon copy. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Hide and Seek or Whipmaster. n.p., 1954; 100 leaves. Typescript, carbon copy. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Unpublished early version of Baby Doll.
- Golden Rules for Playwrights. Acapulco, Mexico, unpublished, 1959; 3 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Night of the Iguana. n.p., play, 1960; 100 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Author's work-script.
- Baby Doll. n.p., undated; 65 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Screen scenario.
  Fragment, not included in film.
- Poems, n.p., 1952 March; 7 leaves (Box 2, Folder 6)
  This file contains typescripts and holographs of five poems: "We Are Coming Home to Die," "Ain't it a Pity," "She that Comes Late to the Dance," "A Witch and her Daughter," and "A Moment in a Room."
- A Man Grows Long... n.p., undated; 5 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Incomplete poem.
- Letter to the drama editor of the New York Times. New York, undated; 2 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Published in a different form in the drama pages of the New York Times.
- A reply to the Point of View (POV) of critic Marya Mannes. New York, undated; 6 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Published in the drama section of the New York Times in a slightly different form.
  First draft.
- Mama's Old Stucco House. n.p., undated; 1 leaf. Holograph. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Story published in final form in The Knightly Quest. New York: New Directions, 1966.
- The Mutilated, and The Gnadiges Fraulein. n.p., undated; 43 leaves. Typescript and holograph. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Two short plays, final versions produced in the 1960s.
- What's Next on the Agenda, Mr. Williams? n.p., undated; 13 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Prose poem describing the author's experiences in the violent ward of a psychiatric hospital.
  Read at London Poetry Festival, 1970.
- A Recluse and His Guest. n.p., undated; 13 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Short story published in Playboy, December 1969.
- The Tread-Mill. n.p., undated; 3 leaves. Typescript. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Fragment of an early short story.
- One Arm. n.p. Screenplay of the short story, unproduced, circa 1968; 100 leaves. Typescript. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Letter to Virginia Carr. Key West, Florida, 1970 August 18-19; 2 leaves. Typescript. (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Maxwell, Gilbert. Tennessee Williams and Friends. New York: World Publishing Company, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Uncorrected proofs, galleys.
- Man Bring This Up Road. n.p., undated; 55 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Short story published in The Knightly Quest. New York, New Directions, 1966.